{
  "reference_number": "12360",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "I also think we should support our neighbouring South Pacific countries to lower their emissions, eg Tonga, Rarotonga, Vanuatu etc\n\n with investment and expert advice and skills."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Only if storms and flooding worsens, so the process can be speeded up."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I agree that their needs to be emissions budgets, but seriously believe that the next five to ten years are crucial to reduce them\n\n drastically. I suggest there be budgets set every 2 years in this time, aiming at reducing all greenhouse gases by 50% by firstly\n decreasing the amount of animals in agricultural, and rapidly planting a variety of trees, native forest at hill land tops, more cropping\n trees for farmers to diversify their land use to, eg nuts, fruit etc as well as developing hemp, rice,flax, manuka and wheat crops, so we\n\n are more self sufficient and less mono intensive crops. At the same time continue increasing Public transport, and offer subsidies to\n low income ind's, students and households. Also invest in inventions to convert current cars to electric, so that the millions of cars on\n the road will not be wasted/trashed. Continue decreasing road freight to rail and open up port trade more for goods to be\n\n transported around NZ, eg Wellington to Kaikoura and Christchurch, Auckland to Gisborne etc and for exports to leave the local ports\n for overseas. Decrease waste to landfill of organics by teaching and promoting composting for indivdual households, as well as\n\n setting up regular greenwaste free pickups. Increase recycling by setting up bottle and can deposit schemes for glass, plastic and\n aluminium cans, which also rewards the consumer to recycle. Increasing Planting in cities on skyscrapers vertically, roof gardens, and\n using empty buildings for growing veges and seedlings hydroponically. Important to encourage all households to have own water\n\n tanks by using recycled plastic to make them cheaply, using grey water for crops and gardens. Promoting dams on farms for irrigation\n use, no more tapping of rivers. Govt and councils encouraging local and community gardens with land, funding and education. The\n\n Govt and Councils promoting Organic Farming and Horticulture, Banning eco toxic sprays immediately eg Neonicitinoid sprays, that\n harm beneficial insects and fish etc in waterways. Managing Landfills better immediately by investing in filtration of emissions and\n planting out areas surrounding the site in lavender and citronella plants to help deal with bad odours. I think these changes will bring\n\n about a 50% reduction in emissions in the ten year period, if not more. From then a 5 year emissions budget could be bought in."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence",
      "answer_index": 14,
      "notes": "The emissions budgets can only result in less emissions targets, ie reducing the greenhouse gas amounts."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Only to lower the rate of emissions, not increase them."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Being that in the next 10 years our emissions are lowered by 50% I think should be the focus."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Business plays an important role in reducing emissions, and changing from farming large amounts of animals to a diversified use of\nland, preferably in smaller lots, will change our landscape, the debt of farmers, and an investment in completing production of\nresources, eg milk to cheese/ice cream not to milk powder for export. Also no more selling of raw timber, only finished products of\n\nplanks, furniture etc. Investment needed in Green industry to recycle tetrapaks and all plastics could be funded by Govt and councils.\nIncreasing information and education to community members via practical workshops on composting and recycling etc held by\n\nCouncil and by schools, so the message gets to Adults, not just school children. Increase incentives to individuals by bottle deposit\nschemes, and offer info in a variety of languages. Encourage change with low interest loans for water tanks, solar power, worm farms\n\netc available via councils, and for Farmers to successfully diversify with low interest loans from Kiwibank and other NZ banks. Because\nwe are losing crops already due to flooding and droughts, we need to change how we grow our produce now."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Also Individuals, Businesses and Councils can be subject to fines and convictions for refusing to comply within deadlines, and that\nEcocide becomes a crime. I am annoyed at the amount of farmers and businesses that make no effort to change things that are\n\nbeneficial for the environment, and basically have been treated very leniently, had deadlines extended and then still carry on with\npolluting the environment etc."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "For example in adapting to different growing conditions, growers should use tunnel houses. For animals, barns and shade need to be\nprovided to manage extreme heat and cold conditions. These should be Nationwide standards that local and regional councils\n\ncannot wiggle out of because there are lots of farmers in roles who only care about costs to themselves etc. With housing not just\nheat but cooling need to be regulated into Warrant of Fitness conditions. There is a need for large institutions to use their facilities\n\nbetter, to provide cooling and heating at schools and hospitals, water tanks, roof gardens, and solar power and other renewable\nenergy sources encouraged."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I agree with mandatory reporting, we need to inspect that community places and businesses are doing what they are saying. To\nencourage uptake by businesses and home owners, rates reductions of 1-5% or tax reductions of 1-5% could be offered as a reward\n\nfor compliance and speed in rectifying problems."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Encourage sharing of information on how to deal with different problems, eg putting houses on stilts, or rocks and plantings on\nforeshore to prevent erosion at the coastline etc. Getting rid of coal based fuel usage should be a priority and using wood waste from\n\npine plantations to make bricks for these boilers, would solve 2 problems at once."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Because we are in need of rapid change, I think that Research and Development Funding should be available for emissions reduction\n\nprojects like converting diesel and petrol cars to electric ones for example. Also encourage more innovation and inventiveness by\noffering support and funding for good and great ideas at all levels of society - Home, Business, Transport, Agriculture, Horticulture,\n\nTourism, in fact you could have competitions for these areas that offer a range of prizes and an easy way to get these\ninnovations/inventions into everyday life. As I have said previously, it is a priority that we change agriculture in NZ, and deal with\nerosion issues to me, and this will also assist in cleaning up our waterways. I do not believe that we should continue in the same way\n\nto run our economy on destroying our environment, and it is time that this was urgently rectified! Thankyou to the Coalition govt that\nhas asked us for our views on this important issue."
    }
  ]
}
